

# Joyce Kao, Ph.D.

Full Stack Data & Image Analyst

2 01 Nov, 1984

US citizen, Swiss B permit

8049 Zürich

+41 78 692 61 77

joyce.kao@biol.ethz.ch

## About Me –

Highly-adaptable, detail-oriented data analyst with extensive experience in complex experimental design, multi-modal data collection, and analyses. Over 10 years coordinating and managing internationally collaborative projects. Currently adding full stack developer skills in a LeWagon bootcamp.

# Languages

English (native)

Chinese (native)

German (B1)

# Technical Skills -

□ Data Science

Hypothesis testing, Regression, Clustering, Survival Analysis, Machine Learning

>\_ R, Python

Image Analysis

Segmentation, Classification

> Fiji, ilastik, CellProfiler, Icy

Web Development

Currently in LeWagon Full Stack Developer Bootcamp

HTML, CSS, SQL, JavaScript, git

## **Selected Experiences**

2019 May-present

#### **Postdoctoral Scientist**

**ETH Zürich** Developing root architecture variation data pipelines while assisting a new lab at the Institute of Plant Biology establish information/communication infrastructure.

#### Key responsibilities & Contributions:

- · Building and optimizing image analysis workflows for biologists to analyze various types of image data.
- Setting up and advising on basic lab informatics structure (i.e. lab communications, lab operational wiki, ordering systems, seed stock database, etc.).
- · Designing experiments investigating root architecture in Arabidopsis arenosa by streamlining workflows for experimental, data collection, and analysis protocols.

2019 Oct-present

#### **Program Director**

ETH Zürich/University of Zürich

Establishing the Open Innovation in Life Sciences program, a new division of Life Science Zurich, that helps life scientists practice open science. https://www.openinnovationlifesciences.com/

## Key responsibilities & Contributions:

- In charge of program development, assembling the operational infrastructure, establishing strategic partnerships, and preparing fundraising documents.
- Designing and launching landing page, and managing online platforms for event registration and social media.
- · Supervising and guiding conference planning committee in organizing the 2020 Open Innovation in Life Sciences conference.

2018 Dec present

#### **Freelance Statistics Consultant**

**Self & Yashina Tutors** 

Recommending and performing statistical analysis on various types of datasets including product and customer satisfaction assessment surveys.

2014 - 2019

## **Postdoctoral Fellow**

New York University

Awarded the NIH Ruth L. Kirschstein Research Service Award to conduct research on effects of genetic backgrounds on chromatin gene perturbations.

#### Key Responsibilities & Contributions:

- Coordinated a team of eight members to perform gene knockouts in over 400 lines of *Drosophila melanogaster*
- · Collaborated with the lab of Ernst Hafen at ETH Zürich to develop an image-based high-throughput assay for quantifying spatial color patterns of insect eyes.

2006 - 2014

**University of Southern California Graduate Research Assistant** Led research projects in bioinformatics, molecular and marine biology, and ecology resulting in four peer-reviewed publications.

#### Key Responsibilities & Contributions:

- · Managed an interchanging team of six undergraduate researchers on multiple simultaneous research projects both in the laboratory and field.
- Performed statistical analyses and coordinated team results for publications.

# Joyce Kao, Ph.D.

Full Stack Data & Image Analyst

## Other skills

- Microsoft Office: Excel, Word, Powerpoint, Outlook, etc.
- G Google Suite: Sheets, Docs, Slides, Cal, etc.
- Communication: Slack, Glip
- Task/Team tracking: Trello

## Hobbies

- Photography, Sewing, Crocheting
- Yoga, Running, Traveling

## **Education**

## Degrees

2006 – 2014	Ph.D. in Computational Biology	University of Southern California
	Publications: bit.ly/jykpub	
2003 – 2006	B.S. in Mathematics	The University of Texas at Austin
	with honors	
2003 – 2006	B.A. in English	The University of Texas at Austin
	with honors and minor in Biology	

#### **Continuing Education**

Spring 2020	Full Stack Developer Bootcamp	LeWagon
Fall 2019	Grundgrammatik: Deutsch A2-B1	Sprachzentrum der UZH & ETHZ
Mar 2019	Business Creation in ICT	Venture Labs

## **Extracurricular Activties**

Volunteering for events, organizations, & initiatives to give back to the community.

2014-now	Science Ambassador Scholarship	Cards Against Humanity
	Reviewing annual applications on the judges	panel for four-year, full-
	tuition college scholarship aimed towards supporting young women	
	studying in STEM fields at U.S. institutions	

2016-now Akademischer Mittelbau am Departement Biologie ETH Zürich Official scientific staff association representing staff interests in shaping departmental policies. Serving as Communications Officer setting up key partnerships with local organizations.

2-5 Feb, 2019

NEUBIAS ECI Bioimage Analysis
Training School
Curated course content and organized trainers to teach image pro-

cessing and analysis for the 3rd annual Network of European Bioimage Analysts (advanced) Early Career Investigators Training School.

The Drosophila post-mating response: gene expression and behav-

2012, 2014 Annual ISMB conference multiple locations
Supervised 30 volunteers at the 20th and 22nd Annual International
Conference on Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology on preparing
event collateral, attendance reporting, session recording, etc.

## **Scientific Communications**

Selected Publications (Full List @ bit.ly/jykpub)

	ioral changes reveal perdurance and variation in cross-tissue inter-	
	actions. G3. DOI: 10.1534/g3.119.400963	
2019	EvoChromo: towards a synthesis of chromatin biology and evolution.	
	Development. DOI: 10.1242/dev.178962	
2018	NEUBIAS 2018 Conference Report. Imaging & Microscopy.	
	https://www.imaging-git.com/news/neubias-2018-0	
2015	Population genomic analysis uncovers African and European	
	admixture in Drosophila melanogaster from the southeastern	
	United States and Caribbean Islands. Molecular Ecology. DOI:	
	10.1111/mec.13137	
	10.111/11160.1313/	

#### Outreach Videos

2020

2018 The Company of Biologists Eve	oChromo workshop:
------------------------------------	-------------------

https://youtu.be/VjcuAZYxWwI

2017 Using flies to study cryptic genetic variation:

https://wp.nyu.edu/siegal/cryptic-genetic-variation/

March 29, 2020

Joyce Kao, Ph.D.